<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Majesties declaration to all his loving subjects, upon occasion of his late messages to both Houses of Parliament, and their refusall to treat with him for the peace of the kingdome. Charles R. Our expresse pleasure is, that this our Declaration be published in all churches and chappels within the kingdome of England and dominion of Wales, by the parsons, vicars, or curates of the same.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78747</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2259</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E126_47</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19891</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860764</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860764</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156187</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78747)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156187)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 22:E126[47])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Majesties declaration to all his loving subjects, upon occasion of his late messages to both Houses of Parliament, and their refusall to treat with him for the peace of the kingdome. Charles R. Our expresse pleasure is, that this our Declaration be published in all churches and chappels within the kingdome of England and dominion of Wales, by the parsons, vicars, or curates of the same.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
                  <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by His Majesties Command at Oxford, by Leonard Lichfield, Printer to the Universitie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The messages of the King and the replies of Parliament are reprinted here.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb: 11th".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156187:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>HIS MAJESTIES</hi> DECLARATION To all His Loving Subjects, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon occaſion of his late</hi> MESSAGES <hi>to both Houſes of</hi> PARLIAMENT, <hi>And their Refuſall to treat with Him for the Peace of the KINGDOME.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <opener>
                           <signed>Charles R.</signed>
                        </opener>
                        <p>OUr expreſſe pleaſure is, That this our Declaration be publiſhed in all Churches and Chappels within the Kingdome of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> by the Parſons, Vicars, or Curates of the ſame.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Printed by His Majeſties Command at <hi>Oxford,</hi> by <hi>Leonard Lichfield,</hi> Printer to the <hi>Univerſitie.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:156187:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156187:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>His Majeſties</hi> DECLARATION <hi>To all his loving Subjects, upon occaſion of his late Meſſages to both Houſes of</hi> Parliament, <hi>and their refuſall, to treate with him for the peace of the Kingdome.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IF it had not evidently appeared to all men who have careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly examined and conſidered Our Actions, Meſſages, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, how far We are and have been from begetting or promoting the preſent Diſtractions, and that the Arms wee have now taken are for the neceſſary ſafety and defence of Our life, being not taken up by Us till our Town and Fort of <hi>Hull</hi> were kept from Us by force of Armes, Our Navy imployed againſt Us to keep all forraigne ſupply of Arms and Mony, when Our owne here was ſeized and detained from Us, and an Army raiſed in pay, and marching againſt Us, yet the late reception of Our Meſſage of the 25. of Auguſt, ſent by Perſons of Honour and Truſt, will ſure ſatisfie the World, that we have omitted nothing on Our part that a gracious and Chriſtian Prince could or can do to prevent the effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſtian Blood, but that the Malignant party, which have with great ſubtilty and induſtry begot this miſunderſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Us and Our good Subjects, reſolve to ſatisfie and ſecure their malice and ambition with the ruine of the Kingdome, and in the blood of Us and all Our good Subjects.</p>
            <p>When they had forced Us, after the neglect of Our Meſſage from Beverley, by raiſing a great Army, and incenſing Our Subjects a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Us, to erect our royall Standard; that Our Subjects might be informed of Our danger, and repaire to Our Succour, though Wee had no great reaſon to believe any Meſſage of Ours would receive a very good entertainment, if thoſe men might prevaile who had brought all theſe miſeries upon the Kingdome to ſatisfie their own private end: yet obſerving the miſerable accidents which already be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell Our good Subjects by the Souldiers under their command, and well knowing that greater would enſue, if timely prevention were not applyed; and finding that the malice and cunning of theſe men had infuſed into Our People a Rumour, that Wee had rejected all
<pb facs="tcp:156187:3"/>Propoſitions and offers of Treaty, and deſired to engage Our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in a Civill War, which Our Soule abhors, wee prevaile with Our ſelfe (for a full expreſſion of Our deſire to prevent the effuſion of Blood) to ſend a gracious meſſage to both Our Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on the 25. of Auguſt, in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>His Majeſties gratious Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to both Houſes of Parl. ſent from <hi>Mottingham</hi> 25. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1642 By the Earls of <hi>Southhamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> and <hi>Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſet,</hi> Sir <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hn C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pepe,</hi> Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, and Sir <hi>William <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>edall.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>VVE have with unſpeakable grief of heart long beheld the diſtractions of this Our Kingdom,
Our very ſoul is full of anguiſh untill We may find ſome remedy to prevent the Miſeries which are alredy to overwhelme this whole nation by a civil War: And though all Our endeavours tending to the Compoſing of thoſe unhappy differences betwixt Us and Our two houſes of Parliament (though purſued by Us with all Zeal and Syncerity) have been hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto without that Succeſſe We hoped for; yet ſuch is our conſtant and earneſt care to preſerve the publike Peace, that We ſhall not be diſcouraged from uſing any Expedient, which by the bleſſing of the God of Mercy may lay a firm foundation of Peace and happineſſe to all Our good Subjects: To this end obſerving that many miſtakes have ariſen by the Meſſages, Petitions and Anſwers betwixt Us and Our two Houſes of Parliament, which happily may be prevented by ſome other way of Treaty, wherein the Matters in difference may be more cleerly underſtood, and more freely tranſacted; We have thought fit to propound to you, That ſome fit perſons may be by you inabled to treat with the like number to be authorized by Us, in ſuch a manner, and with ſuch freedom of debate, as may beſt tend to that happy Concluſion which all good men deſire, <hi>The peace of the Kingdom:</hi> Wherein as We promiſe in the Word of a King all ſafety and encouragement to ſuch as ſhall be ſent to Us, if you ſhall chooſe the place where we are for the Treaty, which We wholy leave to you, preſuming of your like care of the ſafety of thoſe We ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy if you ſhall name another place; So We aſſure you and all Our good Subjects, that (to the beſt of Our underſtanding) nothing ſhall be therein wanting on Our parts, which may advance the True Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, Oppoſe Popery and Superſtition, Secure the Law of the Land (upon which is built as well our juſt Prerogative, as the Propriety and Liberty of the Subject) Confirme all juſt Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Priviledges of Parliament, and render Us and Our Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple truely happy by a good underſtanding betwixt Us and Our two Houſes of Parliament. Bring with you as firm Reſolutions to doe your duty, and let all Our good people joyne with Us in Our prayers to Almighty God for his bleſſing upon this Work.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:156187:3"/>
                  <p>If this Propoſition ſhall be rejected by you, We have done Our duty ſo amply, that God will abſolve Us from the Guilt of any of that blood which muſt be ſpilt, and what opinion ſoever other men may have of Our Power, We aſſure you nothing but our Chriſtian and Pious care to prevent the Effuſion of blood hath begot this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Our Proviſion of Men, Arms and Money, being ſuch as may ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Us from farther violence, till it ſhall pleaſe God to open the eyes of Our People.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Our Meſſengers were not ſuffered to ſit in the Houſes, and one of them, the E. of <hi>Southampton</hi> (againſt whom there was not the leaſt colour of exception or ſo much as a vote) not ſuffered to deliver Our Meſſage, but compelled to ſend it by the Gentleman Vſher, and then commanded to depart the Town, before they would prepare any Anſwer, which they ſhortly ſent Us in theſe words,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Anſwer of the Lords and Commons to his Majeſties Meſſage the 25. of <hi>Aug.</hi> 1642.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>May it pleaſe Your Majeſty,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſembled, having received Your Majeſties Meſſage of the <hi>25.</hi> of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> doe with much griefe reſent the dangerous and diſtracted ſtate of this Kingdom, which we have by all means endeavoured to prevent, both by our ſeverall advices and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions to Your Majeſty, which have been not onely without ſucceſſe, but there hath followed that, which no ill counſell in former times hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, or any age hath ſeen, namely, thoſe ſeverall Proclamations and Declarations againſt both the Houſes of Parliament, whereby their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are declared Treaſonable, and their Perſons Traitors; And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Your Majeſtie hath ſet up Your Standard againſt them; whereby You have put the two Houſes of Parliament, and in them this whole Kingdome out of Your protection; ſo that untill Your Majeſtie ſhall recall thoſe Proclamations and Declarations, whereby the E. of Eſſex and both Houſes of Parliament, and their adherents and aſſiſtants, and ſuch as have obeyed and executed their commands and directions, according to their duties, are declared Traitors, or otherwiſe Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents; And untill the Standard ſet up in purſuance of the ſaid Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations be taken down, Your Majeſtie hath put us into ſuch a condition, that whilſt we ſo remain, we cannot by the fundamentall priviledges of Parliament, the publique truſt repoſed in us, or with the generall good &amp; ſafety of this Kingdome give Your Majeſtie any other Anſwer to this Meſſage.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Joh. Browne Cler. Parliament. H. Elſinge Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb facs="tcp:156187:4"/>
            <p>THis ſtrange Anſwer might well have diſcouraged Us from any thought of proceeding further this way, and informed Us ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently what ſpirit ſtill governed amongſt thoſe few, who conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſtill in both Houſes, otherwiſe after ſo many bitter and inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Meſſages and Declarations ſent to Us, and publiſhed againſt Us, We ſhould not have been reproched with Our Proclamations and Declarations ſet forth by Us, as the effect of ſuch evill Counſel, as was unparallel'd by any former Examples. We beleeve indeed ſuch Proclamations and Declarations have never been before ſet forth; but were former times ever acquainted with ſuch intolerable provocations? were there ever, before theſe Twelve months, Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations publiſhed in the name of either or both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to make their King odious to the People? Have either or both Houſes ever before aſſumed or pretended to a Power to raiſe Arms or levy War in any Cauſe, or can both Houſes together exerciſe ſuch a Power? Are thoſe Actions which the Law hath defined literally and expreſly to be Treaſonable, or ſuch Perſons to be Traitors, not ſo, becauſe they are done by Members of either Houſe, or their appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? And muſt not We declare ſuch who march with Arms and Force to deſtroy Us, to be Traitors, becauſe the E. of Eſſex is their Generall? Thoſe whom We have or doe accuſe, We have named to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with their crimes, notorious by the known Law of the Land, (a favour not granted to our evill Counſellors) and appeal to that known Law to judge between Us: And now that by this we ſhould have put the whole Kingdome out of Our Protection (in whoſe behalfe We doe all that We have done) is a corrupt Gloſſe upon ſuch a Text, as cannot be perverted but by the cunning practices of ſuch who wiſh not well to King or People, yet that no weak perſons might be miſſed by that Imputation upon Us, We ſent a Reply to that Anſwer in theſe words,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>His Majeſties Reply to an Anſwer ſent by the two Houſes of Parliament to His Majeſties Meſſage of the 25. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> concerning a Treaty of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation.</head>
                  <p>VVE will not repeat what meanes We have uſed to prevent the dangerous and diſtracted eſtate of the Kingdom,
nor how thoſe means have been interpreted, becauſe being deſirous to avoid effuſion of blood, We are willing to decline all memory of former bitterneſſe that might make Our offer of a Treatie leſſe readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accepted.</p>
                  <p>We never did Declare, nor ever intended to Declare both our Houſes of Parliament Traitors, or ſet up Our Standard againſt them, and much leſſe to put them and this Kingdom out of Our Protection:
<pb facs="tcp:156187:4"/>Wee utterly Profeſſe againſt it before God and the World. And further to remove all poſſible Scruples which may hinder the Treaty ſo much deſired by Us; We hereby Promiſe, ſo that a day be appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by you for the revoking of your Declarations againſt all Perſons as Traitours or otherwayes, for aſſiſting of Us, Wee ſhall with all cheerfulneſſe upon the ſame day recall Our Proclamations and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, and take down Our Standard: In which Treaty We ſhal be ready to grant any thing that ſhall be really for the good of Our Subjects; Conjuring you to conſider the bleeding condition of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the dangerous condition of <hi>England,</hi> in as high a degree as by theſe Our offers We have declared Our Self to do: And aſſuring you that Our chief deſire in this is to beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t a good underſtanding &amp; mutuall confidence betwixt Us and Our two Houſes of Parl.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Meſſage produced an Anſwer little differing from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, like men who had no other meaſure of the Juſtice of their cauſe, then their Power to oppreſſe Us, forgetting their own duties, they ſharply informe Us of Ours in theſe words,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The humble <hi>Anſwer</hi> and <hi>Petition</hi> of the Lord and Commons Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, unto the Kings laſt <hi>Meſſage.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>May it pleaſe Your Majeſty,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IF we the Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſembled, ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat all the wayes we have taken, the endeavours we have uſed, and the expreſſions we have made unto Your Majeſtie to prevent thoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions and dangers Your Majeſtie ſpeaks of, likely to fall upon this Kingdome, we ſhould too much inlarge this Reply. Therefore as we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, ſo ſhall we onely let Your Majeſtie know that we cannot recede from our former Anſwer for the reaſons therein expreſſed. For that Your Majeſtie hath not taken down Your Standard, recalled Your Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Declarations, whereby You have declared the Actions of both Houſes of Parliament to be Treaſonable, and their Perſons Traitors. And You have publiſhed the ſame ſince Your Meſſage of the <hi>25.</hi> of <hi>Aug.</hi> by Your late Inſtructions ſent to Your Commiſſioners of Array, which Standard being taken downe, and the Declarations, Proclamations and Inſtructions recalled, If Your Majeſty ſhall then upon this our Humble Petition, leaving Your Forces, returne unto Your Parliament, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their faithfull advice, Your Majeſtie will find ſuch expreſſions of our fidelities and duties, as ſhall aſſure You that Your Safety, Honour and Greatneſſe can onely be found in the affections of Your people, and the ſincere counſels of Your Parliament, whoſe conſtant, and undiſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged endeavours and conſultations have paſſed through difficulties un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of, onely to ſecure Your Kingdoms from the violent Miſchiefs &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:156187:5"/>dangers now ready to fall upon them, and every part of them, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve better of Your Majeſtie, and can never allow themſelves (repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting likewiſe Your whole Kingdome) to be ballanced with thoſe perſons whoſe deſperate diſpoſitions and counſels prevaile, ſtill ſo to interrupt all our indeavours for the relieving of bleeding <hi>Ireland,</hi> as we may fear our labours, and vaſt expences will be fruitleſſe to that diſtreſſed Kingdom. As Your preſence is thus humbly deſired by us; So is it in our hopes Your Majeſtie will in Your reaſon beleeve, there is no other way then this, to make Your Self happy, and Your Kingdom ſafe.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Joh. Brown Cler. Parl.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>VVIthout any bitterneſſe or reprehenſion of their neglect of Us, and the publique Peace, to expreſſe Our deep ſenſe of the Calamities at hand, We yet once more (hoping to awake them to a Chriſtian tenderneſſe towards the whole Kingdome) ſent to them in theſe words,</p>
            <p>VVHo have taken moſt wayes, uſed moſt endeavours, &amp; made moſt reall expreſſions to prevent the preſent diſtractions and dangers, let all the World judge, as well by former Paſſages as by Our two laſt Meſſages, which have been ſo fruitleſſe, that (though We have deſcended to deſire and preſſe it) not ſo much as a Treaty can be obtained, unleſſe We would denude Our ſelfe of all force to defend Us from a viſible ſtrength marching againſt Us, and admit thoſe Perſons as Traitors to Us, who according to their duty, their Oaths of Allegiance, and the Law, have appeared in defence of Us their King and Liedge Lord (whom We are bound in Conſcience and honour to preſerve) though We diſclaimed all Our Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; Declarations, &amp; the erecting of Our Standard as againſt our Parliament. All We have now left in Our Power is to expreſſe the deep ſenſe We have of the publike miſery of this Kingdom, in which is involved that of Our diſtreſſed Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to apply Our ſelf to Our neceſſary defence, wherein We wholy rely upon the Providence of God, the Iuſtice of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Cauſe, and the affection of Our good People, ſo farre We are from putting them out of Our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection. When you ſhall deſire a Treaty of Us, We ſhall piouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member whoſe blood is to be ſpilt in this quarrell, and cheerfully em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it: And as no other Reaſon induced Us to leave Our City of <hi>London,</hi> but that with honour and ſafety We could not ſtay there, nor raiſe any force but for the neceſſary defence of Our Perſon and the Law, againſt Leavies in oppoſition to both; ſo we ſhall ſuddenly
<pb facs="tcp:156187:5"/>and moſt willingly returne to the one, and disband the other, as ſoon as thoſe cauſes ſhal be removed. The God of heaven direct you, and in mercy divert thoſe judgements which hang over this Nation, &amp; ſo deale with Us and Our Poſterity as We deſire the Preſervation &amp; Advancement of the true Proteſtant Religion, the Laws and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Subject, the juſt Rights of Parliament, and the Peace of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>BUt as if all theſe gracious Meſſages had been the effects onely of Our Weakneſſe, and inſtances of Our want of Power to reſiſt that torment, they deale at laſt more plainly with Us, and after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſharp, cauſeleſſe, and unjuſt reproaches, they tell Us in plaine Engliſh, that without putting Our Self into their hands, and deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Our own Force, and the protection of all thoſe who have faithfully appeared for Vs according to their duty, there would be no means of a Treaty, although Our extraordinary deſire of Peace had prevailed with Vs, to offer to recall Our moſt juſt Declarations, and to take downe Our Standard, ſet up for Our neceſſary defence, ſo their unjuſtifiable Declarations might be likewiſe recalled, their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer follows in theſe words,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The humble <hi>Anſwer</hi> of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in Parliament unto His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties</hi> laſt <hi>Meſſage.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>VVE the Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſembled, doe preſent this our humble Anſwer to Your Majeſties Meſſag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the <hi>11.</hi> of this inſtant month of <hi>September,</hi> when we conſider the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, Rapines, Firing of houſes, Murthers, (even at this time, whilſt Your Majeſty propounds a Treaty) committed upon Your good Subjects by Your Souldiers, in the preſence, and by the Authority of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, being of the number of thoſe whom Your Majeſty holds Your Selfe bound in Honour and Conſcience to Protect as Perſons doing their Duties. We cannot think Your Majeſty hath done all that in You lies to prevent, or remove the preſent deſtractions; nor ſo long as Your Majeſty will admit no Peace, without ſecuring the Authors and Inſtruments of theſe miſchiefs from the Iuſtice of the Parl. which yet ſhall be ever di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenced with all requiſite moderation &amp; diſtinction of offences, Although ſome of thoſe Perſons be ſuch in whoſe Preſervation Your Kingdome cannot be ſafe, nor the unqueſtionable Rights and Priviledges of Parl. be maintained, without which the power and dignity thereof will fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to contempt. We beſeech Your Majeſty therefore to conſider Your expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, That God ſhould deale with You and Your Poſterity, as Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty deſires the preſervation of the juſt Rights of Parliament, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing undeniable in the Trying of ſuch as we have declared to be Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents,
<pb facs="tcp:156187:6"/>we ſhall beleeve Your Majeſty both towards Your Self and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament will not in this Priviledge, we are moſt ſenſible of, deny us that which belongs unto the meaneſt Court of Iuſtice in this Kingdome. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath Your Majeſtie cauſe to complain that You are denyed a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, when we offer all that a Treatie can produce, or Your Majeſtie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, Security, Honour, Service, Obedience, Support, and all other effects of an Humble, Loyall, and faithfull ſubjection, and ſeek nothing but that our Religion, Liberty, peace of the Kingdome, ſafety of the Parliament may be ſecured from the open violence, and cunning practices of a wicked party, who have long plotted our ruine and deſtruction; And if there were any cauſe of Treaſon, we know no competent perſons to Treat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the King and Parliament, And if both Cauſe and Perſons were ſuch as could invite Treatie, the Seaſon is altogether unfit, whilſt Your Majeſties Standard is up, and Your Proclamations and Declarations unrecalled, whereby Your Parliament is Charged with Treaſon.</p>
                  <p>If Your Majeſtie ſhall perſiſt to make Your Self a ſhield and defence to thoſe Inſtruments, and ſhall continue to reject our faithfull and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary advice for ſecuring and in intaining Religion and Liberty, with the peace of the Kingdome and ſafety of the Parliament; we doubt not but to indifferent judgements it will eaſily appeare who is moſt tender of that Innocent Bloud which is like to be ſpilt in this Cauſe; Your Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, who by ſuch perſiſting, doth endanger Your Self and Your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, or We, who are willing to hazard our ſelves, to preſerve both.</p>
                  <p>We humbly beſeech Your Majeſty to conſider how impoſſible it is, that any Proteſtation, though publiſhed in Your Majeſties Name, of the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of the miſcries of Your Proteſtant Subjects of <hi>Ireland,</hi> of Your Reſolution to maintain the Proteſtant Religion, and Laws of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, can give ſatisfaction to reaſonable and indifferent men, when at the ſame time divers of the Iriſh Traiters and Rebels, the known favourers of them, and Agents for them, are admitted to Your Majeſties preſence with grace and favour, and ſome of them imployed in Your ſervice; when the Cloathes, Munition, Horſes, and other Neceſſaries bought by Your Parliament, &amp; ſent for the ſupply of the Army againſt the Rebels there, are violently taken away, ſome by Your Majeſties command, others by Your miniſters, and applyed to the maintenance of an unnaturall War againſt Your People here.</p>
                  <p>All this notwithſtanding as we never gave Your Majeſty any juſt cauſe of withdrawing Your Self from Your great Councell, ſo it hath over been, and ſhall ever be far from us to give any impediment to Your return, or to neglect any proper means of curing the diſtempers of the
<pb facs="tcp:156187:6"/>Kingdome, and cloſing the dangerous Breaches betwixt Your Majeſty and Your Parliament, according to the great Truſt which: lies upon us, and if Your Majeſty ſhall now be pleaſed to come back to Your Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without Your Forces, we ſhall be ready to ſecure Your Royall Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Your Crown and Dignity, with our Lives and Fortunes: Your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in this Your great Councell, being the onely means of any Treaty betwixt Your Majeſty and them with hope of Succeſſe.</p>
                  <p>And in none of our deſires to Your Majeſty ſhall we be ſwayed by any particular mans advantage, but ſhall give a clear Teſtimony to Your Majeſtie, and the whole world, that in all things done by us, we faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intend the good of Your Majeſty, and of Your Kingdoms, and that we will not be diverted from this end by any private, or ſelfe-reſpects what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Joh. Brown Cler. Parl.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>THey will not beleeve We have done all that in Us lyes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and remove the preſent Diſtractions, becauſe of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, Rapines, and the like committed upon Our good Subjects by Our Souldiers. Let them remember who have compelled Vs, and againſt Our Soules deſire forced Vs to raiſe thoſe Souldiers, and then if the oppreſſions and Rapines were indeed ſuch as are falſely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, Our poore Subjects who ſuffer under them, will looke on them, and onely on them, as the Authors of all the miſeries they doe or can undergo. We confeſſe with grief of heart ſome diſcords have and many more may befall Our good People by Our Souldiers, but We appeal to all thoſe countyes through which We have paſſed, what care We have taken to prevent, and what Juſtice We dayly inflict upon ſuch Offenders: neither hath the leaſt complaint been ever made to Vs of violences and outrages, which We have not to Our utmoſt Power repayred or puniſhed, however thoſe falſe and treaſonable Pamphlets are ſuffered, which accuſe Vs of giving war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for plundring of Houſes. Our Mercy and Lenity is ſo well known to the contrary, that it is uſually made an excuſe by thoſe who againſt their Conſciences aſſiſt this Rebellion againſt Vs, that they chuſe rather to offend Vs upon confidence of Pardon, then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke thoſe Malignant Perſons who without charity or Compaſſion deſtroy all who concur not with them in faction and opinion. How far We are from Rapine and Oppreſſion may appear by Our Lenity to the Perſons and Eſtates of thoſe who have not only exerciſed the Militia (the ſeed from whence this Rebellion againſt Vs hath
<pb facs="tcp:156187:7"/>growne) but contributed Money and Plate to the maintenance of that Armie which now endeavours to deſtroy Vs, As of <hi>Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Leiceſter,</hi> and many other places through which we have paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, many of whom then were and now are in that Army: to let paſſe Our paſſing by Chartly (the houſe of the E. of <hi>Eſſex</hi>) without other preſſures then as if he were the Generall of Our owne Army, and Our expreſſe Orders to reſtraine the Liberty, our Souldiers would other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have uſed upon that place, and his Eſtate about it. How con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary the proceedings are of theſe great Aſſertors of the publique Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, appears fully by the ſad inſtances they every day give in the pundring by Publick warrant, the Houſes of all ſuch whoſe Duty, Conſcience, and Loyalty hath engaged them in our Quarrell, which every good man ought to make his owne. By their declaring all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be out of the Protection of Parliament (and ſo expoſing them to the fury of their Souldiers) who will not aſſiſt this Rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Vs, their anointed King, by the dayly outrages committed it. Yorkſhire, when contrary to the deſire and agreement of that County (ſigned under the hands of both partyes) they will not ſuffer the Peace to be kept, but that the diſtractions and Confuſion may be univerſall over the whole Kingdom, direct their Governour of Hull to make Warr upon our good Subjects in that County, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the robbing and plundring the Houſes of all ſuch who concur not with them in this Rebellion. Laſtly, by the barbarous, ſacrilegious Inhumanity exerciſed by their Souldiers in Churches, as in Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, Worceſter, Oxford, and other Places, where they committed ſuch unheard of outrages, as Iewes, and Atheiſts, never practiſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. God in his good time will make them examples of his ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance.</p>
            <p>We never did, nor ever ſhall deſire to ſecure the Authors and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of any miſchiefs to the Kingdom from the Iuſtice of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, We deſire all ſuch Perſons may bee ſpeedily brought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne puniſhment by that Rule w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is or ought to be, the Rule of all puniſhment, the known Law of the Land, If there have ſeemed to be any interruption in proceedings of this nature, it muſt be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, how long Perſons have been kept under generall Accuſations, without tryall, though earneſtly deſired, that the Members who were properly to judge ſuch Accuſations have by violence been dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thence, or could not with honour and ſafety be preſent at ſuch debates, that notorious Delinquents by the knowne Lawes were protected againſt Us from the Iuſtice of the Kingdom, and ſuch cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:156187:7"/>Delinquents, who committing no Offence againſt any knowne Law were ſo voted onely for doing their Duties to Us, and then there will be no cauſe of complaint found againſt Us.</p>
            <p>And for the Priviledges of Parliament We have ſaid ſo much and upon ſuch reaſons, (which have never been anſwered but by bare poſitive Aſſertions) in Our ſeverall Declarations, that We may well, and doe ſtill uſe the ſame expreſſion, That We deſire God may ſo deale with Us and Our Poſterity, as We deſire the preſervation of the juſt Rights of Parliament; the violation whereof in truth by theſe deſperate Perſons is ſo cleerly known to all men who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Priviledges of Parliament, that their rage and malice hath not been greater to Our Perſon and Governement then to the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Priviledge, and very being of Parliaments, witneſſe their putting in, putting out, and ſuſpending what Perſons they pleaſe, as they like or diſlike their opinions, their bringing down the Tumults to aſſault the Members, and awe the Parliament, their poſting and proſecuting ſuch Members of either Houſe as concurred not with them in their Deſignes, and ſo driving them from thence for the ſafety of their lives, their denying Us, againſt the known, eſtabliſhed Law, and the Conſtitution of the Kingdome, to have a negative voice, without which no Parliament can conſiſt, their making cloſe Committees, from whence the Members of the Houſes are exempted, againſt the Liberty of Parliament, and laſtly reſolving both Houſes into a cloſe Committee, of ſeventeen perſons who undertake and direct all the preſent Outrages and the managery of this Rebellion againſt Us, in the abſence of foure parts of five of both Houſes, and without the privity of thoſe who ſtay there, which is not onely contrary but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to Parliaments themſelves. By theſe groſſe, unheard-of Incaſions and breaches of the Priviledges of Parliament, (and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them they could not have done the other) They made way for their Attempts upon the Law of the Land, and the Introduction of that unlimited, Arbitrary Power which they have ſince exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed to the intolerable damage and confuſion of the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And We aſſure Our good Subjects, the vindication of theſe juſt Liberties and Priviledges of Parliament, thus violated by theſe men, is not leſſe the Argument of Our preſent quarrell and underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, then Our owne Honour, Intereſt, and Safety, thoſe being no way ſo ſecurely to be preſerved, as by preſerving Parliaments and their juſt Priviledges. Neither is there any Proteſtation to Our knowledge publiſhed in Our name of Our tenderneſſe of the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb facs="tcp:156187:8"/>of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Our Reſolution to maintain the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and Laws of this Kingdom, that is not the Proteſtation of Our Soule, and manifeſted in all Our Actions, and We hope that falſe Scandall, That divers of the Iriſh Traitors and Rebels, the known favourers of them, and Agents for them are admitted to Our preſence with favour, and imployed in Our ſervice, will gaine no credit with good men, who remember well the notorious impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation ſo confidently and groundleſly heretofore caſt on Us by M. <hi>Pym,</hi> of which as there could never be the leaſt proof, ſo Wee could never receive any ſatisfaction for that high injury, which might have been a warning to them to have publiſhed no more ſuch untruths, if they had not found that truth and their End, cannot meet together.</p>
            <p>For the Horſes taken for Our ſervice, which were provided for the ſervice of Ireland, 'tis true We were compelled for the bringing Our own wagons from Cheſter for the carriage of Our Munition to make uſe of them, being few in number and of ſmal value, after they were certified to be of no uſe for the ſervice, for which they were provided. And for the clothes upon enquiry Wee finde that ſome few were taken by Our Souldiers (but without order from Vs) going to Coventry, and as was probably beleeved for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of that place, then in actual rebellion againſt Vs, but how far We have beene, and are from diverting any of thoſe proviſions made for the reliefe of that poore Kingdome (the thought of whoſe miſerable condition makes our heart bleede) may appeare by our expreſſe command, given for the ſpeedy tranſportation of 3000. ſuites of clothes which we found provided at Cheſter, but neglected to be ſent, and which no neceſſity of our own Army here could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile with Vs to ſeiſe. And how bold ſoever the reproaches of that kinde have beene upon us, VVe are conſulent malice it ſelfe cannot lay the leaſt probable imputation upon us, for the neglect of our duty towards that Kingdome. VVhat one thing in our power have wee neglected or omitted, which might contribute to the aſſiſtance, or eaſe of our poore Proteſtant ſubjects there? VVe firſt recommended the caſe of that buſineſſe to both our Houſes of Parliament. VVee condeſcended to all propoſitions made on the behalf offered to raiſe 10000. Voluntiers (which if then accepted had ſhortned that work) offered to venture our own perſon in the ſervice, what interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that offer of ours found, is known to all the world, VVe parted with our Intereſt in the Land of the Rebels, to encourage ſuch who were willing to adventure in that buſineſſe, and when money
<pb facs="tcp:156187:8"/>is raiſed by our conſent for that ſole purpoſe, they have at once ſeized 100000. pound particularly appointed by Act of Parliament for the reliefe of Ireland (our Army being ready to periſh for want of it) and employed it to maintain this unnaturall civill war at home. They have levyed men and entertained Commanders for that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and then compelled them to joyne in this Rebellion, and to march againſt Us, and though they have complained of Our keeping the Lieutenant of Ireland ſome weekes with Us, (when in truth it was a ſeaſon of extraordinary buſineſſe) after We had in vaine for many months preſſed his diſpatch, yet themſelves now detain him, when his going is ſo neceſſary for the preſervation of that Kingdom. And no doubt theſe men (and theſe alone) by begetting this miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſtraction of <hi>England,</hi> are guilty before God and Man of all the inſupportable calamities that Our Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> endures. Let all the world judge where the deſire of Peace is, and upon whoſe account the blood and confuſion which hath been ſhed and muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, ſhall bee caſt, And whether the ſeverall Proclamations and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations publiſhed by Us, have notbin extorted from Us, by ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of Inſolencies and Injuries, which no former times ever pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, neither can any ſober man wonder, when We are publickly reproached, traduced, and reviled to Our People (a practice never known till this Parliament) that We endeavour by a true relation and Declaration of Our Actions and Intentions, and of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracyes, who have vowed Our deſtruction, to informe Our good Subjects of the cunning and malice they are to encounter with; and when a Combination is entred into to deſtroy Us, and to alter the Religion and Law of the Kingdome, and to that purpoſe an Army raiſed and marching againſt Us, that We proclaime the Generall of that Army and ſuch who ſhall aſſiſt him in leavying a War againſt Us, to be Traitors, and have ſet up Our Royall Standard, and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all Our good Subjects to come to Our defence. And yet both in that Proclamation and in all Our Declarations We have never ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed Our Parliament, but ſuch factious, ſeditious members of both Houſes whom We have named, and whom We are ready to prove according to the Rules of the known Law to bee guilty of High Treaſon. We well know, and all the Kingdome knowes that of neere 500. Members which the Houſe of Commons contains, there remains not now there 100. neither hath above ſuch a number con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented almoſt to any thing of which We have ever complained, the reſt have either been driven away by Tumults and Threats of the
<pb facs="tcp:156187:9"/>Perſons whom We have accuſed, or out of Conſcience withdrawne themſelves from their deſperate conſultations, and of about 100. Peeres o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Realme there are not above 15. or 16. who concur in theſe miſerable Reſolutions, which diſturbe the publique peace, many of which being of deſperate fortunes, have no other ſupport, then the Commands now given them to make War upon Us, and now theſe men muſt ſit upon the lives and fortunes of all the Nobility, Gentry, and Commons of England, and becauſe We will not put Our ſelfe into the hands, Government, and diſpoſall of them, all Our good Subjects are envited and encouraged to Rebel againſt us, yet We haue beene, and are ſtill far from accuſing all that ſmall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of both Houſes who are yet left together, VVe believe many of them are miſled by the cunning and malice, and frighted by the power of thoſe men whom we have accuſed, againſt every one of whom We have evidence of matter of fact, that the knowne Law of the Land determines to be High Treaſon.</p>
            <p>And now that all Our good Subjects may ſee how deſirous theſe men and their adherents are to prevent the effuſion of blood, and the laſting miſeries of a Civill War, they will make themſelves ſo conſiderable, that except We will recall Our Proclamations and Declarations whereby particular men named for particular Actions (which the Law hath defined to be Treaſon) are ſo accuſed, and others war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from involving themſelves in their guilt, and except We will take downe Our Standard, that Our good Subjects may not repaire to Us for Our defence, when ſo many Armies are raiſed againſt Us in ſeverall parts of the Kingdom, and ready to deſtroy Us, and ſuch of Our good Subjects, who dare continue loyall to Us, and except We will return to London, from whence with violence We have been driven, We muſt not be treated with, or receive any Anſwer to ſo gratious a Meſſage.</p>
            <p>It can no longer be doubted by any man, who hath not wilfully forſaken his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that it is no more a quarrell undertaken by the Parliament, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived and fomented by the Perſons We have named, and now continued ſolely in their defence, to whoſe Ambition, Faction, and malice, the true reformed Proteſtant Religion, the juſt Right, Honour, Safety, and life of Us and Our Poſterity, the Law of the Land, which hath ſo long preſerved this Nation happy, the Liberty of the Subject eſtabliſhed by that Law, and the glorious frame and conſtitution of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom muſt be ſacrificed. But as We have hitherto left no Action unperformed, which in Honour, Iuſtice and Conſcience We were obliged to doe, or in Chriſtian Policy and Prudence We could conceave might probably prevent theſe Calamities, ſo We thanke God he hath given Us a full Courage and Reſolution to run the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt hazard of Our life for the ſuppreſſion of this horrible Rebellion, in the which no diſproportion of Power, Armes, or Money ſhall diſcorage Us; And We hope that all Our good Subjects; beſides, by the Common duty of Allegiance, will be ſtirred up for their owne ſakes, for the preſervation of the bleſſed Proteſtant Religion, and for the upholding this whole admirable frame of Government, which being diſſolved, all their private and particular Rights &amp; Intereſt muſt be immediately confounded, to bring in their utmoſt power &amp; aſſiſtance unto Us in this deſperate exigent. And We doe declare that whoſoever ſhall looſe his life in this Service for Our defence, the Wardſhip of his Heyre ſhall be granted by Us without Rent or Fyne to his owne uſe, and VVe ſhall hold Our Selfe obliged to take all poſſible care for the ſupport, relief, and protection of all their wives, and Children, who ſhall have the hard for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to dye in this Service.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
